愿万能的主 赐予怜悯
Misereatur vestri, omnipotens Deus.
宽恕汝之罪孽
Et dimissis peccatis vestris omnibus.
愿耶稣基督
Perducat vos Jesu Christos.
引领你到达永生
ad vitam aeternam.
阿门
Amen.
虔诚的英格兰人民
To the faithful people of England,
托马斯·莫尔爵士与红衣主教费施尔
your Holy Father offers you.
以身殉教
the hand of condolence,
我悲痛不已
his tears of grief.
心中怒火难以平息
and his anger at the martyrdom.
我谨在此哀悼亡灵
of Sir Thomas More and Cardinal Fisher.
他们的死讯震惊了整个基督教界
Their murder has shocked the whole of Christendom.
处决二位伟大而高尚之人
It was an unpardonable sin against.
即是对上帝和我们神圣的教会
God and our Holy Church, in whose name.
犯下了不可饶恕的罪行
these two great and noble men died.
我们为那些继续存活于
We pray for those in England.
英格兰暴政统治下
who must continue to live under tyranny.
担惊受怕的人们祈祷
and in fear for their lives and for their souls.
我们祈祷国王
We pray the King.
不再听信谗言
ceases to listen to evil counsel.
回归正道 信奉真理
and returns to obedience and the true faith,
现在还为时不晚
before it is too late.
我们向圣母玛利亚祈祷
We pray to Marian, Mother of God,
英格兰能够
that England may be.
摆脱异端邪教的控制
redeemed from heresy,
异教徒及其种种邪恶行径
and all its evil ways,
正在引导她走向
and from the clutches of the heretics.
被诅咒的毁灭之路
who even now, are leading her towards destruction and damnation!
乔治·波林 洛克福特勋爵
George Boleyn, Lord Rochford,
将与莫尔雷勋爵之女成婚
is to marry Lord Morley's daughter.
是 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
莫尔雷勋爵求见于我
Lord Morley came to see me.
他无法满足托马斯·波林阁下
He cannot meet Sir Thomas Boleyn's.
300磅嫁妆的要求
demand for a dowry of 300 pounds.
我承诺为他补足差额
I assured him that I would make up the shortfall.
陛下甚是慷慨
Your Majesty is most generous.
对修道院的调查进展如何
How is your survey of the religious houses progressing?
陛下 负责调查的专员
Majesty, the Commissioners are currently.
目前在西南部的修道院进行核查
examining houses in the west country.
他们向我汇报
There, and elsewhere, they tell me.
在各地修道院皆发现了骇人听闻的罪恶行径
they have uncovered many enormities.
什么罪恶行径
What enormities?
他们发现
They have found.
修道士和众多修道院
the monks and many places.
如此堕落 放肆 腐败
so depraved, so licentious.
以至于诸位专员
and so corrupt that your commissioners.
对理想的改革感到绝望
already despair of any perfect reformation.
例如 著名的黑尔斯圣血
For example the case of the celebrated Holy Blood of Hailes.
理应为圣徒之血
Supposedly the blood of a saint,
用于抚慰那些为寻奇迹而来的朝圣者
used for healing the pilgrims who flock there hoping for a miracle,
事实上 杯中所盛之物为鸭血
it turns out to be the blood of a duck,
由修道士们定期更换
which the monks renew regularly.
鸭血…
Duck's blood…
那么 克伦威尔阁下
Well, Mr. Cromwell,
你建议我们怎么做
what do you propose we do about it?
恕我直言 陛下
If Your Majesty will forgive me,
私以为应寻求途径宣传
I think we should be looking for ways to promote.
陛下的新君主制
your Majesty's New Monarchy.
有何高见
What do you have in mind?
可通过排演戏剧达成目的
One way would be through the production of plays.
何以见得
Why plays?
戏剧是阐明政见的最佳方式
Plays are an ideal way of setting forth,
将罗马派别的主教们可憎
before the people's eyes,
邪恶的面目 告白于天下
the abomination and wickedness of the Bishop of Rome.
与此同时 向民众传达
They're also a means to demonstrate to people.
无论是依据宗教还是世俗的法律
the obedience that as subjects they owe,
臣民都理当服从于国王陛下
by God's and man's laws, to Your Majesty.
好提议
Good.
那么 我将戏剧的资金筹措和排演事宜
Then, I leave it to you, Mr. Secretary,
交由你处理
to finance and produce some plays.
我们必须竭尽所能
We must do all we can…
推动改革
to advance our revolution…
我即将从容就死
that I shall now suffer death in.
殉教于神圣的天主教会的信仰
And for the faith of the Holy Catholic Church.
- 大人 - 大臣阁下
- My Lord. - Mr. Secretary.
主教大人
Your Grace.
既然勋爵大人对改革充满热情
Since Your Lordship makes no secret of your zeal for reform,
我们也迫不及待地向你汇报改革的进展
we were anxious to let you know our progress.
国王陛下已告知我
His Grace has just informed me.
在坎特伯雷大教堂设立新职位
of an important new appointment at Canterbury Cathedral.
的确 西蒙·海斯博士已被任命为新教长
Indeed. Dr. Simon Heyes has been made our new Dean.
海斯博士对圣像画甚感厌恶
Dr. Heyes particularly detests the cult images.
决意将它们从大教堂铲除
and is determined to removed them from the Cathedral.
同时引入新学
as well as introducing the new learning.
将改革派安置于教会其中
It's vital that we place reformers.
尤为重要
in positions of responsibility inside the Church.
费施尔及莫尔自私的殉教行为
There's bound to be a reaction to the.
定会引起风波
self-serving martyrdoms of Fisher and More.
因此需要告诫臣民
Which is why I'm letting it be known, throughout the Kingdom,
若听到朋友或邻居
that if anyone hears a friend or a neighbor,
对国王及其婚姻或是改革发表评论
criticizing the King or his marriage or the reforms,
他们有义务揭发不敬之事
they have a duty to report it.
与此同时 克伦威尔阁下
At the same time, Mr. Cromwell.
我们有义务宣传正面消息
we have a duty to spread the good news.
新君主制的实质在于
If the New Monarchy is about anything at all.
自由
then it is about liberty!
破除旧迷信 摆脱恐惧和罪恶
Liberty from old superstitions, from fear and guilt.
引领我们从黑暗走向光明
We… we are moving, my friends, from darkness into light.
我深有同感
I'm in agreement with Your Grace.
幸运的是 我们拥有了
Fortunately, we have a new weapon.
推广理念的新利器
to promote our ideas.
我的上帝 此为何物
Oh, my Lord! What in God's name is that?
这叫印刷机 大人
It's called a printing press, my lord.
它将改变世界
And it will change the world.
你在想什么
What are you thinking of?
没什么
Nothing.
容妾身向您禀明
May I say something?
您知道国外有很多人
You know there are many people abroad,
或许国内也有这样一些人
and perhaps even some within this Kingdom,
仍然质疑我们女儿的正统地位
who still question the legitimacy of our daughter.
千真万确
It's true.
确有其事
You know it's true.
但我们得有所作为来改变这一切
But there is something we can do to change everything.
如果伊丽莎白
If Elizabeth was betrothed.
与法兰西斯国王最小的儿子
to King Francis's youngest son,
昂古莱姆公爵联姻
the Duke of Angouleme,
那么她的正统地位将不再
then her legitimacy and station would no longer.
遭到质疑
be questioned by anyone.
所言极是
I agree,
我已有所考虑
and have already thought about it.
我会召见法国大使
I will speak to the French Ambassador.
今夜您是否会临幸于我
Will you come to my bed tonight?
亲爱的托马斯
Dear Thomas!
- 陛下 - 留在宫庭吧
- Majesty. - Come and stay at court.
- 我需要你 - 去转告他们 我不会签署的
- I need you. - I'm not going to sign it! Go and tell them!
民众会以为
People are going to know that.
英格兰国王朝令夕改
the King of England is easily changeable!
难道国王就得令人畏惧三分？
Is it better for a King to be feared?
我无意担任大法官一职
I don't want to be chancellor.
或是被人爱戴？按我的旨意行事
Or loved? You will do as I command!
哈利 哈利 我来此递交我的辞呈
Harry. Harry. I come to offer my resignation.
称呼我哈利的时代已不复存在
The time for Harry is over!
我愿意解除你的职务
I discharge you most willingly.
你的头 将被砍下 你的身体
Your head, cut off. Your body,
将被分成四部分
to be divided in four parts.
请原谅我
Please forgive me.
托马斯？
Thomas?
托马斯…
Thomas…
怎么了？
What is it?
我改变主意了
I've changed my mind.
我不想结婚了
I don't want to go through with it.
我说 亲爱的
Now, now, sweetheart.
每个女人在这时都会有点胆怯
Every woman has a moment of faintheartedness.
这很正常
It's natural.
不行
No!
你要嫁给一个大家族
You are marrying into a great family.
无论你喜不喜欢 这婚都得结 明白了吗
You will do it, whether you like it or not. Do you understand?
向全能的主祷告
Benedicto Dei, omnipotentis.
圣父 圣子
Patris et Filii.
圣灵…
et Spiritus sancti…
老实点
Get on with it!
阿门
Amen!
各位同胞 今天我们齐聚一堂
Brethren, we are gathered here today.
国王陛下 亨利·诺里斯爵士觐见
Majesty, Sir Henry Norris.
亨利爵士
Sir Henry.
- 国王陛下 - 有什么能帮忙的吗
- Your Majesty. - What can I do for you?
也许国王陛下也听说了
Well as Your Majesty may know,
我最近成了鳏夫
I recently became a widower.
所以 我自然想要续弦
And so, naturally, I am looking to wed again.
而我心仪的人
And my choice has fallen.
正巧是王后陛下的侍女之一
upon one of Her Majesty's ladies.
- 谁？- 玛格丽特·谢尔登女士
- Who? - Lady Margaret Sheldon.
- 你是说玛琪 - 是的
- You mean Madge! - Yes.
是的 我知道和她很熟的人
Yes, I believe some people call her that.
是这么称呼她的
If they are familiar with her.
你向谢尔登女士表白了吗 亨利爵士？
Have you made your intentions plain to Miss Sheldon, Sir Henry?
还没有陛下 目前
No, Your Majesty. I have merely.
我还只是单方面的爱慕
admired her from a distance.
但现在我想有更进一步的发展
But I would now like to take things further.
如果陛下…
If Your Majesty can think of no…
不反对？
impediment?
不 一点也不反对
No. None.
我恩准了
You have my permission.
我们相识已久
I have known you a long time.
没有人比你更为诚实 受人尊敬
I could not think of a more honest nor a more honorable man.
陛下 非常感谢
I am deeply grateful to Your Majesty.
亨利爵士
Sir Henry.
陛下
Your Majesty.
法国大使阁下觐见
His Excellency the French Ambassador.
- 阁下好 - 国王陛下想要见我？
- Excellency. - Your Majesty wanted to see me?
我想问候一下我的兄弟
I wanted to ask after my brother, the King.
国王陛下很好
His Majesty is very well.
除了对皇帝的憎恶之心不减
Except for his hatred of the Emperor,
- 这成了他的心病 - 那么他仍希望我们维持旧好？
- which is like a disease. - So he still wants our friendship?
我的上帝 您是世上他最爱戴的王公
Mon Dieu! He loves you above all the princes in the world.
那我想向他提议
Then make to him this proposal.
他的儿子查尔斯
that his son Charles,
昂古莱姆公爵
Duke of Angouleme,
与我深爱的女儿 伊丽莎白订婚
should be betrothed to our beloved daughter, Elizabeth.
她是谁？
Who is she?
简·帕克
Jane Parker.
莫尔雷勋爵的女儿 他是国王的远房表亲
Lord Morley's daughter. He's a distant cousin of the King…
但她是个女孩子
But she's a girl.
有什么好笑的？
Was that funny?
不知道
I don't know.
亲爱的
Sweetheart.
你真的爱我吗 乔治
You do love me, don't you, George?
当然是真的 我娶了你不是吗
Of course I love you. I married you, didn't I?
我非常期待今晚的来临
Oh, I can't wait for tonight.
- 怎么了？- 没事 我…
- What is it? - Nothing. I…
失陪一下 父亲
Excuse me, father.
你真漂亮
You're very pretty,
漂亮的简
Pretty Jane.
不要
No.
求求你了 不要
No, please…
求你了
No, please.
求你不要…
Please don't…
让我们来讨论些其他事
Let us go about our other matters.
鉴于约翰国王对
Now as much as King John.
神圣教会的所作所为
does Holy Church so handle,
我将用十字架 书本
so here I curse him with cross,
铃铛和蜡烛 诅咒于他
book, bell and candle…
我将恳请上帝
I will ask God.
收回照耀他的永恒圣光
to put him from His eternal light.
我将把他带离耶稣的身边
I will take him from Christ,
在这铃声之后…
and after the sound of this bell…
铃声 你这傻小子
The bell, you buggers!
铃声
The bell!
在这铃声之后
And after the sound of this bell.
我说之后 在这铃声之后
I said after the sound of this bell…
他的躯体和灵魂
Both body and soul,
都将被送给地狱的魔鬼
I will give him to the devil in hell!
- 同时… - 这出戏真不错 大臣阁下
- And meanwhile… - This is a fine piece of work, Mr. Secretary.
很有教育意义
And educative.
是谁写的？
I wonder who wrote it?
贝尔先生
Ah, Mr. Bale.
他曾是旧教的牧师
He was once a priest of the old faith,
但看清了历史趋势之后
but seeing how things went on,
就化身为积极的改革者
became a most passionate reformer.
你知道 我们家族最引以为豪的事
You know, I think our family never did anything better.
莫过于协助您
than facilitate and encourage.
支持您的高升 大臣阁下
your own rise, Mr. Secretary.
我也相信 您不会忘了我们为您做的一切
And I trust you never forget that we did so.
主教
And Bishops,
将会赚进大笔大笔的钱
will make lots and lots of money.
我爱教皇 一生挚爱
I love the Pope, as much as I ever may be.
我真诚地向你请教 这是为什么呢？
I pray thee heartily, tell me why you do so?
因为我悟性好
Because I perceive well,
教皇他喜欢吹大牛
the Pope is a jolly fellow.
文质绉绉 富得流油
A trim fellow, a rich fellow.
像个讨喜的小丑
Yes, and a merry fellow!
他大权握在手…
He's rich in his royalty…
信徒们全成了他的哈巴狗
and angelic to his behold!
我和法国大使谈过了
I've talked to the French Ambassador.
法兰西海军元帅被任命来筹备这次订婚仪式
Francis is sending the Admiral of France to arrange the marriage.
谢谢
Thank you.
两位陛下好
Majesties.
法兰西海军元帅即将造访我国
The Admiral of France is to pay an official visit.
我希望你以我之名招待他
I want you to receive.
要让他觉得宾至如归
and entertain him on my behalf.
为什么是他？
Why him?
我想我的父亲才是更合适的人选吧
Surely my father would be a much better choice.
我相信大人您能办好这件事
I trust Your Grace to carry out my commands.
我将一直是
I am, as ever,
陛下您最忠诚谦卑的仆人
Your Majesty's humble and obedient servant.
多此一举
That was unnecessary.
- 他恨我 - 但他爱我
- He hates me. - But he loves me.
既然是用拉丁文写的…
As they're in latin…
没人会懂了
no man can know.
怎么了？
What is it?
那个娼妓
That woman is a whore!
她对我简直连我对狗还不如
She treats me worse than I treat my dogs.
但你的狗会反咬一口
But then your dogs bite back!
如果典礼和迷信将从我们这里消亡
If ceremonies and superstitions from us fall,
那么 和僧侣 教规
then farewell monks and canons,
牧师 修道士 主教…
priest, friar, bishop…
一切的一切都道别吧
and ALL.
凯瑟琳王后怎么样？
How is Queen Katherine?
她身体欠安
Alas she is very unwell.
病情不断恶化
She is sinking.
她的日常开销不仅大大被削减
Not only is her household severely reduced,
还被禁止与亲生女儿相见
but she has been separated from her daughter.
- 长达4年 - 这太残忍了
- for the last 4 years. - That is very cruel.
但她的信念是坚定不移的
But her faith is astonishing.
那玛丽小姐呢？
And the Lady Mary?
只要那个情妇还掌权
While the concubine has power,
我担心她性命不保
I fear for her life.
为国家的安康
To the comfort of this nation!
请为我们祈求
Precibus et meritis beatae.
圣母玛利亚…
Mariae semper Virginis…
玛丽小姐 您抱着伊丽莎白公主
Lady Mary. What in heaven's name are you doing.
有何企图？
with the Princess Elizabeth?
她被独自丢在这里
She was left alone.
我来抱抱她
I took care of her.
把她给我
Give her to me.
你把她一个人撇下 你个蠢货
You left her alone. You little fool!
我们品着酒 缅怀那些离我们远去的人
We sup and think of those who are no longer with us:
为莫尔和费施尔等诸多忠义之士干杯
To More and to Fisher, those martyred men.
愿上帝保佑他们
God bless them.
据说
I am told that many who.
很多最初支持国王推行改革的人士
initially supported the King's reforms.
现在都颇有微词
are now forming a different opinion.
很多忠义之士的遇害
The terrible murders.
终于让大家觉醒了
of honest and faithful men has opened many eyes.
我仍然不会归罪于国王
I still do not blame the King.
他被巫术迷惑了
He has been seduced by witchcraft.
我一直这么想
I've always believed it,
- 现在我证据在握了 - 你有证据？
- and now I have proof. - You have proof?
对
Yes.
我和安妮的一位侍女
I have befriended.
交情甚好
a maid of Anne's bedchamber,
她告诉我那个贱人藏着一个惊天的秘密
who has told me that the harlot hides a secret.
她是个畸形人 乔普斯
She's deformed Chapuys,
左手多长了片指甲
an extra fingernail on her left hand,
为了隐藏它 她痛苦不堪
which she is always at great pains to conceal.
她的身上长满了痣
As well her body is covered in moles,
你知道 这便是恶魔之刻印
which is sometimes called, the Devil's Teats as you know.
这个侍女
Now, this maid,
向我发誓 她在安妮裸露的皮肤上
she swore to me honestly that she had seen these quite plainly.
清清楚楚地看到了
on Anne's naked skin,
尽管她一直在试图掩盖
Even though the lady constantly seeks to cover herself.
哦 天哪
My God!
此事当真？
Is it so?
千真万确
It's is truth.
所以她必须得死
That is why she must die.
怎么了
What is it?
他的风流韵事层出不穷
He's having more affairs.
你肯定？
Are you sure?
我当然肯定
Of course I'm sure.
我经常找不到他 没人会透露他的行踪
Often I can't find him. No one will tell me where he is.
我知道 他出宫了
He leaves the palace. I know that.
有时他一走就是好几个小时
He's gone for hours sometimes.
我想他可能在别处另设后宫了
I think he's got a harem somewhere.
他可以在那里
There's a place where he keeps his harem,
金屋藏娇 我知道
where he keeps his women. I know it.
安妮
Anne.
我要大难临头了
Something's going to happen to me.
- 不 - 你知道那个预言
- No! - You know there's a prophecy.
人人都知道 预言说
Everyone knows it. The prophecy says.
有一位英格兰王后将会被烈火焚烧而死
A Queen of England will be burned.
别胡思乱想了
Don't talk like this.
你一定会平安无事的
Nothing is going to happen to you.
我没能为国王生个太子
I'm unable to give a King a son;
太子
A son.
传承其父亲的血脉
to be the living image of his father.
没事的 一定会没事的
It's all right. Everything is going to be all right.
别哭
Please don't cry.
我爱你
I love you.
我发誓 我会照顾你的
I'll look after you, I swear.
拜托别哭了
Please don't cry.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
大臣阁下 这些是什么？
Mr. Secretary. What are all these?
启奏书
Denunciations.
据报在图克斯伯利的一位教士
It is reported that a canon at Tewksbury,
不知有意或是无意的为凯瑟琳王后祈祷
mistakenly or otherwise, offered prayers to Katherine the Queen.
而非安妮王后
Other than Anne.
他所辖教会中 有七人呈供了上述逆词
Seven of his congregation reported these words.
- 你准备怎么处置他 - 我什么都不做
- What will you do to him? - Nothing.
他已年逾古稀了
He's near 80 years old.
这纯粹是一种无意识的口误
An absent-minded slip of the tongue.
对于这样一个老人 实在是情有可原
in such an old man is perfectly forgivable.
其他的一些案件
Some of these others.
涉及问题则更加严重
are much more serious.
看看这些
Look at these.
这些小册子是在颂扬国王陛下
The tracts praising His Majesty.
及其新君主制和他所倡导的改革
and his New Monarchy and the reformation they explain.
解释了改革的必要性
Why the reformation is necessary.
以及改革为国王
and the liberties and the opportunities.
卑微的臣民所带来的自由和机会
it would be bringing to the King's humblest subjects.
令人深思啊
It's very impressive.
大臣阁下 您的成就值得庆贺啊
You are to be congratulated on your industry, Mr. Secretary.
不过难道你就丝毫不担心
But does it never concern you.
国王权力过大
that the King has taken to himself.
不受制约
an absolute power,
从而导致重修宪法？
without any constraint, to remake the law?
让国王高兴的不就是… 重订宪法？
Is not that which pleases the King… the law?
我 我只是随便说说…
I was… I was only observing…
怀特阁下 我很欣赏你 我喜欢与你共商国事
I like you, Mr. Wyatt, and enjoy your company.
不过 听闻阁下吃喝嫖赌无一不精
But you have a reputation:
你臭名远扬
You gamble and you whore.
你善于见风使舵
You sail close to the wind.
苍天不容
God forbid.
你理应触礁而亡
It should ever blow you onto the rocks.
法兰西海军元帅
His Excellency Philippe Chabot de Brion,
布里昂的菲利浦·夏博阁下驾到
Admiral of France.
- 大人 - 在下是夏博元帅
- Your Grace. - Admiral Chabot.
本人万分荣幸地欢迎您以及随从人员
It is my privilege and pleasure to welcome you and your party.
到访英格兰 光临此地
to my home and to England.
请允许我向您引见内人 公爵夫人
May I present my wife, the Duchess.
能一睹夫人风采 实在是荣幸之至
Madame. Je suis ravi de vous connaître.
请允许我
And, with your permission,
向你引见我的秘书埃尔阿尔封斯·贡蒂哀先生
may I present my Secretary, Monsieur Alfonse Gontier…
- 夫人 - 公爵大人
- Madame. - Your Grace.
这位是我的侄女 杰曼尼小姐
And my niece, Mademoiselle Germaine.
杰曼尼小姐 您实在是太美了
Mademoiselle. You are very pretty.
夫人 大人
Madame. Your Grace.
大人 能否告诉我 接下来有何安排
So tell me, your Grace, what are we to expect?
这里先由我来招待您及各位随从人员几天
I am to entertain you and your staff here for a few days.
随后国王陛下会在皇宫设宴款待
Then the King invites you to dine at court.
- 很好 - 还有件事
- Very good. - There is one other thing:
我被告知 安妮王后
I am told that Queen Anne.
特意为您安排了一个宴会
has planned a banquet in your honor.
和一场网球赛
And a tennis match.
我肯定
I believe you met Her Majesty.
您在加来见过王后陛下
once before, in Calais,
当时她还未加冕 陪行伴驾于国王左右
when she accompanied His Majesty before her coronation.
也许吧 不过我不记得有这么一次会面了
I may have. But I have no recollection of any such meeting.
还有 很遗憾 我不打网球
And, alas, I don't play tennis.
我们进去吧
Shall we?
早安 约翰
Good morrow, John.
陛下
Your Majesty.
- 你要去哪 - 出宫去 - 哪儿？
- Where are you going? - Out. - Where?
回去
Go back inside.
你要去哪 快说
Where are you going? I want to know.
与你何干
It's none of your business.
我倒希望你马上进宫去
It is my pleasure that you go back inside. Now.
遵命 陛下
Majesty.
小姐
Mademoiselle.
我喜欢你 阁下
I like you, Excellency.
你机智过人
You're very clever.
但我不喜欢你们皇帝的待人态度
But I don't like the way your Emperor treats me.
就凯瑟琳而论 他似乎认为
He seems to think that, as far as Katherine is concerned,
就是我在泄私愤
that I act out of spite,
或是我心肠歹毒
or that I am being malicious.
可我发誓 绝对不是那么一回事
But I swear it's not true.
我觉得 我应该
I suppose I ought.
心满意足了 因为我知道世人
to be content in the knowledge that the world knows.
明白我受了多少的诬陷
the many wrongs that have been done to me.
我知道 你不赞成我在王国内推行的改革
You don't approve of the changes I'm making in this kingdom.
克伦威尔截获了一些你的信件
Cromwell intercepts some of your letters.
过去我们常把它叫做 人道主义
We used to call it Humanism.
我 渥西和莫尔
Wolsey, More and me.
我们都是人道主义者
We were all Humanists.
很多人都觉得我变了 可我一点都没变
Most people think I've changed, but I haven't.
在内心深处 我依然是个人道主义者
At heart I'm still a Humanist.
乔普斯
Chapuys,
我向你保证
I promise you.
我即将在国内推行的改革
that I am going to make such a reformation in this kingdom.
将会使我在基督教界
that I shall be remembered eternally.
永垂不朽
throughout all Christendom.
我丝毫不怀疑
I have no doubt whatsoever.
陛下的统治无论如何都将永被铭记
that Your Majesty's reign will always be remembered.
我为他准备了一场盛宴
I had planned a banquet in his honor…
- 谁？- 法国海军元帅
- Who? - The French Admiral.
他来了2个星期
He has been here for 2 weeks already,
却只和沙福克公爵呆在一起
staying with the Duke of Suffolk,
甚至连个问安的口信都没送来
and he has not yet sent me a message of goodwill.
任何其他法国使节都会来问安
Every other French envoy has always done so.
他也没有请求觐见我
Neither has he requested an audience with me.
觐见我 堂堂英格兰王后
With me, the Queen of England.
而他此行目的正是来商讨我女儿的未来
and when we are discussing the future of my own child.
陛下该就寝了
Your Majesty should rest.
- 我该告退了 - 据说他还和
- I ought to leave you…- They also tell me he has struck up an acquaintance.
皇帝的大使乔普斯暗通款曲
with the Imperial Ambassador, Chapuys.
这真是太不寻常了？
Is that not extraordinary?
跟我说 他怎能如此？
Tell me why should he do such a thing?
你为何一声不吭 马克？
Why do you not say anything, Mark?
请陛下宽恕 我不知该说什么
Your Majesty must forgive me.I don't know what to say.
这些事情我不胜置评
These matters are beyond my competence.
我只是个舞师
What am I? Only a dancing-master.
更有甚者
And then there's something else:
有人 可能是个恨我的贱人
Someone, some bitch who probably hates me…
告诉我说国王特意安排了
Told me that the King has deliberately invited.
很多漂亮女人进宫
a lot of beautiful women to court.
以迎接元帅的来访
for the Admiral's visit.
你能相信吗？
I mean can you believe that?
- 公爵大人 - 国王陛下
- Your Grace. - Your Majesty.
请容我为你引见
May I present his Excellency,
法国海军元帅 布里昂的菲利浦·夏博阁下
Philippe Chabot de Brion, the Admiral of France.
- 参见陛下 - 欢迎光临我的王宫
- Majesty. - Welcome to my court.
请让我介绍我的妻子 安妮王后
Allow me to introduce my wife, Queen Anne.
夫人
Madame.
请 我们入席吧
Please, let us be seated.
来点葡萄酒吗？
Some wine?
- 当然 - 是哪个地区的酒？波尔多的吗？
- Of course. - Which domain does it come from? Is it Bordeaux?
- 是英国酒 - 英国酒？
- This is English wine. - English wine?
英国从罗马时代起就开始酿酒
We have been making wine in England since the Romans.
光阴短暂如斯？
As recently as that?
很好
Très bien.
果香浓郁
It's very fruity.
很烈 像是…
And strong. Like a…
角斗士的汗水 （春药）
gladiator's sweats! Ha! Ha! Ha!
那位先生是谁？
Who is that gentleman?
我的秘书 贡蒂哀先生
My secretary, Monsieur Gontier.
我想把他介绍给我妻子
I should like to introduce him to my wife.
失陪
Excuse me.
很高兴认识您 女士
Enchanté, mademoiselle.
陛下
Majesté…
陛下 请您宽恕我未能出席
Your Majesty must forgive me.
您为我举办的盛宴
for not being able to attend the banquet you arranged in my honor.
很不巧 但沙克福公爵大人
It was most unfortunate, but His Grace the Duke of Suffolk,
和他那迷人的妻子
and his charming wife,
让我深陷他们的庄园之中
have kept me a virtual prisoner in their castle.
我… 怎么说好呢？
I was… how shall I say?
盛情款待无法脱身
Imprisoned by affection.
夫人？我说话惹您见笑了吗？
Madame? Are you amusing yourself at my expense?
对不起 先生
Forgive me, Monsieur.
我实在忍不住笑出声来
I could not help laughing.
吾王本欲介绍你的秘书给我
at the King's proposition of introducing your secretary to me.
却在见到他时
For whilst he was finding him,
因遇到漂亮女士而全然忘掉初衷
he met that pretty lady, and forgot the whole thing.
言归正传吧
Let's talk some business.
你主人如何交代给你
What instructions do you have from your master,
我女儿伊丽莎白与昂古莱姆公爵的联姻事宜？
with regard to the betrothal of my daughter Elizabeth to the Duke of Angouleme?
陛下他很遗憾 此项提亲不可能
His Majesty regrets that such a proposition is impossible.
为何「不可能」？
Why "impossible"?
虽然他深爱陛下 但国王无法同意
Much as he loves Your Majesty, the King cannot agree.
让他心爱的儿子…
to betroth his beloved son to a…
迎娶其合法地位未得到保禄教皇陛下
to a bride whose legitimacy is not accepted by his Holiness Pope Paul,
及神圣教会
by Holy Church itself,
甚至于神圣罗马皇帝认可的新娘
nor even by the Emperor.
不过 吾王陛下
However, His Majesty,
为示亲善 另行提婚
to demonstrate his love, proposes another match.
他将应允法王太子
He would consent to the betrothal of the Dauphin…
与你合法的女儿玛丽女士的婚约
to Lady Mary, your legitimate daughter.
如果您不同意这桩婚事
If you do not agree to the match, my master.
我主人便会让王太子迎娶神圣罗马皇帝之女
will marry his son to the Emperor's daughter…
将会使贵国孤立于欧洲
leaving your country isolated in Europe.
阁下 您与陛下的会面结束了
Excellence, your audience with His Majesty is now over.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我没有任何借口 凯瑟琳
I have no excuses, Catherine.
我原以为那种日子已经离我而去了
I thought those days were behind me.
也许本性难移
Perhaps human nature can never change.
我发誓 绝不再发生
I swear to you it will never happen again.
我太爱你了
I love you too much.
我无权请你相信我
I have no right to ask you to believe me.
但这是真的
But it's true.
你看
You see…
你毕竟还是令我落泪了
you did make me cry, after all.
她是谁？
Who was she?
你指谁？
Who was who?
在你去找贡蒂哀先生时
That lady you were talking to,
你与她谈话的那个女士
when you were supposed to be finding Monsieur Gontier.
我不知道
I don't know.
是你的情妇之一吗？
Is she one of your mistresses?
你有多少情妇？
How many do you have?
都叫什么名字？
What are their names?
把她们都安置在何处？
Where do you keep them?
有人密报我 你的那些贵族们
Someone told me that your nobles,
像布兰顿之流 一直在帮你沾花惹草
like Brandon, are assisting you in having your affairs.
就此打住吧
That's enough.
不
No.
不 你告诉我 你总是告诉我
No. You told me… you always told me.
我们该彼此诚实
that we should be truthful with each other.
你说这是爱的真谛
You said it was the definition of love.
那么我来告诉你真相
Then here's the truth:
你最好闭上眼睛
You must shut your eyes and endure…
就像你的前任对你一样忍受下去
like your betters have done before you.
你怎能跟我这么说？
How can you say that to me?
你难道不知道我爱你强过凯瑟琳千倍
Don't you know that I love you a thousand times more than Katherine ever did!
你难道不知道 我可以迅速把让你捧上天
And don't you know that I can drag you down.
也可以立刻把你拉下马
as quickly as I raised you?
你该庆幸你还有张床 夫人
This is lucky you have your bed already, madam,
因为如果你没有 我便不会再给你
because if you did not, I wouldn't give it to you again.
弗兰西斯不接受婚约
Francis won't accept to the betrothal.
- 为什么？- 你觉得呢？
- Why? - Why do you think?
因为教皇 他还有神圣罗马皇帝
Because the Pope and he and the Emperor.
全都认为她是私生子
all agree she's a bastard!
全都认为你并非我妻子
And you are not my wife!
告诉我 你的凯瑟琳近来如何？
Tell me: how's your Catherine?
她很好
She's fine.
事实上 她怀孕了
In fact… she's with child.
你真是个幸福的已婚男人 查尔斯
Ah! You're a happily married man, Charles.
我徒有健羡
I envy you.
你认为天体是否影响我们的生活？
Do you think the planets influence our lives?
我不知道
I don't know.
我过去经常与莫尔谈论这方面问题
I would often discuss the issue with More.
在夜里我们会站在屋顶上 揣摸天际
We would stand on the roof at nights, and study the heavens.
莫尔对星空知识甚为熟捻
More had a great knowledge of the stars.
也了解它们如何影响我们的…
and how they influence our…
心态
humors.
现在我为莫尔所发生的一切感到悔恨
I regret now what happened to More.
有时甚至企盼它从未发生
In some ways I wish it never happened.
但这并非都是我的错
But it wasn't all my fault.
每当我打消决心
Whenever my resolve weakened,
每当我心生救他之念
whenever I was inclined to save him…
有个人便会私下
a certain person would privately.
逼迫我加紧他的毁灭
urged me on to his destruction.
何许人？
Who?
你知她是谁 查尔斯
You know who she is, Charles.